<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>MSKCC Patient Education</title>
  <subtitle></subtitle>
  <icon></icon>
  <updated></updated>
  <id>http://patiented.herokuapp.com/feed.xml</id>
  <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://patiented.com"/>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Your Implanted Port</title>
      <published>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</published>
      <updated>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Your Implanted Port&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This booklet will tell you about your implanted port. A port may also be called a BardPort®, a Mediport®, a PowerPort®, or a Port-A-Cath®. There are many different ports available. (Figure 1) Your doctor will choose the one that is best for you and your treatments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A port is like an artificial vein. There are many reasons to have a port placed. Some people have veins that are difficult to start an IV for medicine or draw blood from for tests. Some people need to receive chemotherapy continuously for several days. Sometimes, chemotherapy must be given in a vein larger than the ones in your arms. The port allows medicine to be delivered into your bloodstream through a large vein. The port is made from materials that are safe for long-term use in the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Port&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implanted ports can stay in place for years. The port should make treatments more comfortable for you. You will be able to get intravenous (IV) fluids safely and easily. It is usually possible to have blood drawn for tests from the port. Some ports are specially designed for use during CT scan examinations. Your doctor will let you know if you have one of these ports. They are called “power-injectable” ports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An implanted port is made up of two parts: the port and a catheter. (Figure 1) The port is a reservoir for fluids that will flow through the catheter. It has a raised center or septum made from a self-sealing rubber material. The catheter is a small plastic flexible tube. It is connected to the port which sits under your skin. The other end of the catheter sits in a large vein near your heart. A special needle is inserted through the septum to deliver IV fluids or medicine. The medicine moves from the port through the catheter and into the bloodstream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A port is the size of a nickel or a quarter. It can be circular, oblong, or triangle shaped.  It is usually placed about an inch below the center of your right collarbone. The port usually raises your skin about ? inch above normal. You will most likely be able to feel it through your skin. (Figure 2) It will probably not be seen when wearing a V-neck sweater.  It most likely will not be placed in the area of a bra strap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A specially trained nurse can put a needle into your port through your skin. This is called “accessing” your port. (Figure 3) Some implanted ports have two septas. You can put a needle in each septum. This is called a double lumen port. It is used for patients that need more than one point of access.  If there is only one port, it is called a single lumen port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Port Placement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ports are placed either in Interventional Radiology or in the operating room. This is a short procedure. An IV line will be placed in your arm for the procedure. You will be given medicine through your IV that will make you feel drowsy. It will control pain and anxiety. The area where the port will be inserted will be cleaned and numbed with local anesthetic. You will be given anesthetic in two places, your neck and your chest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The doctor makes a small incision (less than a half inch) above your collarbone. Another incision (one - two inches) is made under your collarbone. A tunnel is formed under the skin between the two openings. The catheter is passed through this tunnel and then gently threaded into the vein. The doctor makes a pocket under the skin, where the port is placed. This pocket will be sutured (sewn) closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;After the Procedure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the procedure, you will have one of the following on the site:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two small dressings covering the two incisions. If you have these dressings do not get them wet or remove them for three days unless your doctor tells you to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A clear, firm skin adhesive, called Dermabond®. Sometimes small pieces of tape cover the Dermabond. The Dermabond will stay in place until it wears off. Do not pick or scratch it off. Do not apply lotion or place adhesive on top of the dressing. This could disrupt the Dermabond and interfere with healing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If the port will be used that day, an access needle will be in the port covered by a dressing. There will also be a small dressing over the top incision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is common for the incision site to feel sore. This pain should lessen within 24 to 48 hours. You can take over-the-counter pain medicine if you need it. Most patients do not need prescription pain medicine. Wearing a seatbelt may put pressure on your incisions. If so, you can put a small pillow or folded towel between the strap and your body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first few days, you should avoid certain activities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not do exercises that involve forceful reaching or stretching.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not lift anything over 10 pounds while your incision is healing. This is usually about two weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While you have your port, do not play any contact sports.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Once your incision heals, you will be able to return to your normal daily activities. You can swim with the port once your skin has healed and as long as there is no needle in the port. The skin over the port only requires normal washing and bathing. You do not need a bandage if the port is not being used. When the port is used, a transparent dressing will cover the needle. It must be kept in place and dry. Most people will not know that you have a port. The port will not set off metal detectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Caring For Your Port&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your port will need to be flushed every four weeks when not being used. This is done to make sure the port catheter does not become blocked. If your port becomes blocked, it will no longer work and may have to be removed. The catheter is flushed with a medicine called heparin. Heparin keeps clots from forming. Please notify your doctor if you are allergic to heparin. You will need a special type of port. Flushing your port needs to be done by a specially trained nurse. Do not allow someone to access your port who is not familiar and trained in port access. Your port will also be flushed right before the needle is removed after each treatment or infusion. If your port is properly maintained, it can stay in place for as long as your doctor feels you need it.  It will be removed during a procedure that is similar to how it was put in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the insertion, call your doctor if:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have pain at the site that is new or has increased.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You notice swelling or a growing bruise at the site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You notice pus or fluid coming from the incision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The incision is hot, tender, red, or irritated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You develop a fever greater than 101° F (38.3° C).
Use the contact information listed below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Contact Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your port was placed in the operating room, please call the office of the physician who placed the port.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doctor &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;_____________  Telephone &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nurse &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;______________  Telephone &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 5 p.m. and on weekends, call the Urgent Care Center at (212) 639-7203 and ask to speak with a nurse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your port was placed in Interventional Radiology, use the following contact information:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monday through Friday, 9AM to 5PM, call 212-639-2236 and ask to speak to a nurse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After hours and on the weekends, call the paging operator, 212-639-2000 and ask for the Interventional Radiology Fellow on call.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
      <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://patiented.com/articles/your-implanted-port"/>
      <id>http://patiented.com/articles/your-implanted-port</id>
      <author>
        <name>MSKCC Patient Education</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Resources for Wigs and Hairpieces</title>
      <published>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</published>
      <updated>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center, we understand that it can be difficult to experience hair loss. Below, you will find resources for wigs and hairpieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Manhattan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angels of New York        &lt;br/&gt;
161 East 61st Street              &lt;br/&gt;
New York, NY 10021            &lt;br/&gt;
(212) 838-7888            &lt;br/&gt;
www.angelsofny.com/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nicholas Piazza
16 West 56th Street, 2nd Floor&lt;br/&gt;
New York, NY 10019&lt;br/&gt;
(212) 838-6190&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Top Priority Prosthetics for Hair Loss            &lt;br/&gt;
174 Fifth Avenue
New York, NY 10010                    &lt;br/&gt;
(212) 206-6785&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Brooklyn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Claire Accuhair       &lt;br/&gt;
1611 Cedar Street         &lt;br/&gt;
Brooklyn, NY    11230             &lt;br/&gt;
(718) 998-6043            &lt;br/&gt;
www.claireaccuhair.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yaffa Wigs
4118 13th Street          &lt;br/&gt;
Brooklyn, NY 11218&lt;br/&gt;
(718) 436-4280
www.yaffawigs.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Queens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ginza Wigs*
116-01 Queens Boulevard
Forest Hills, NY 11375
(718) 544-1848
www.ginzawig.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Long Island&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jackis Wig Works              &lt;br/&gt;
3381 Merrick Road                 &lt;br/&gt;
Wantagh, NY 11793                         &lt;br/&gt;
(516) 679-4633            &lt;br/&gt;
www.jackiswigworks.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wig Salon
1008 West Jericho Turnpike
Smithtown, NY 11787
(631) 864-7560
www.thewigsalonli.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Westchester County&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JA Alternatives                                &lt;br/&gt;
141 Central Avenue, Suite 303                     &lt;br/&gt;
Hartsdale, NY 10530                   &lt;br/&gt;
(914) 723-0034                &lt;br/&gt;
www.oggiadameve.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oggi, Adam &amp;amp; Eve &lt;br/&gt;
770 Central Avenue
Scarsdale, NY 10583
(586) 985-0576
www.hairloss-hair-replacement.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tiffany Wigs
100 Triangle Shopping Center
Yorktown Heights, NY  10598
(800) 427-9447
www.tiffanywigs.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Connecticut&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allura Salon &amp;amp; Day Spa              Anthonys Wigs
23 West Putnam Avenue               Hawley Lane Mall
Greenwich, CT 06830                 Trumbull, CT 06611
(203) 869-1234                  (800) 421-9447
www.allurasalon.com                 www.anthonyshairstylists.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;New Jersey&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AAA Wigs                      &lt;br/&gt;
682 Morris Turnpike                                   &lt;br/&gt;
East Hanover, NJ 07936
(973) 376-8050&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just For You
37 Mt. Pleasant Avenue
Short Hills, NJ 07078
(973) 887-5930
www.justforyoucenter.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lillian Lee Salon and Spa*
947 Teaneck Road
Teaneck, NJ 07666
(201) 837-6770&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For woman only.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Financial Support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;American Cancer Society
www.cancer.org&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some American Cancer Society offices offer free wigs to cancer patients. If you are interested in this service, go to your local American Cancer Society office or call (800) 227-2345.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cancer Care
www.cancercare.org
Cancer care offers free wigs to cancer patients. Call (800) 813-4673 and ask to speak to a social worker.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
      <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://patiented.com/articles/wig-and-hairpiece-resources"/>
      <id>http://patiented.com/articles/wig-and-hairpiece-resources</id>
      <author>
        <name>MSKCC Patient Education</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>When Your Doctor Recommends a Transfusion</title>
      <published>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</published>
      <updated>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Your doctor has recommended a blood transfusion. Many people have questions about why they need a blood transfusion. Some worry about the risk of AIDS or other viruses. The answers to some of the most commonly asked questions are included in this booklet. If you have additional questions, please ask your doctor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Why is a transfusion necessary?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blood transfusions are given to replace blood that has been lost through disease, surgery, or other treatment. Sometimes surgery results in the loss of a large amount of blood. Some diseases and some treatments can lower the number of certain cells in the blood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cells in the blood do many things.  Red cells carry oxygen to the tissues, platelets help form clots to prevent bleeding, and white cells help fight infections. Blood transfusions may be necessary to replace the amount of blood, the cells, or both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Does it hurt?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only pain involved is when the needle is inserted in the vein. The pain is brief. If you have an indwelling catheter, the blood may be given through it. This does not hurt at all. If you have a Mediport, it will be the same needle stick that you have for chemotherapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How long does it take?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A transfusion of red blood cells usually takes two to four hours. Transfusions of other blood components, like platelets, takes only 15-30 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes about four hours for the blood to be released to the unit so the patient can get it. If it is needed urgently, it can be done in two hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Are there risks associated with blood transfusions?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, blood transfusions have some risks. These risks include the very slight chance of having an allergic reaction or acquiring an infection through tainted blood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How can I be sure the blood is safe?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After it is donated, the blood is tested for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syphilis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hepatitis B and C&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exposure to the AIDS virus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The presence of a virus associated with a very rare form of leukemia.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;West Nile virus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trypanosoma Cruzi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The chance of getting any of these from donated blood is very small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Can a friend or relative donate specifically to me?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, friends and relatives can donate both red blood cells and platelets. These are called directed donations. They are tested in the same way as other donations.  If any of the blood tests are positive, the donor is notified privately. The person to whom the blood is directed is told only that the blood is not available. If the blood type is not compatible with the patients, the red blood cells are released into the Blood Banks general inventory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Directed donations will be held for a patient for 30 days. After that, the blood goes into the general inventory. It can then be given to any patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Can anything bad happen during or after the transfusion?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transfusions sometimes cause reactions. The most common symptoms are fever, chills, and hives. These can be treated with a variety of medicines. Transfusion reactions are rarely life threatening. Nursing staff constantly check all patients while a blood transfusion is taking place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How can I be sure the blood I receive is the same type as mine?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your blood is one of the following blood types: A, B, AB, or O and it is either Rh positive or Rh negative. Your blood type is checked with a test called a type and crossmatch. The results of the test are used to match your blood type with the blood in our Blood Bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Can I give blood for myself?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under  certain circumstances the Hospital encourages patients scheduled for surgery to donate their own blood. It is stored and given back if and when you need it. This is called an autologous donation. Ask your doctor if you can donate your own blood. If this is possible, arrangements will be made with the Blood Bank for you to begin banking your blood. Autologous blood donations may be given several times during the month before surgery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What if I don't want a blood transfusion?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is always your right as a patient to refuse a treatment your doctor thinks is best. Doctors recommend a transfusion only when they think it is necessary. A large amount of blood is commonly lost during some types of surgery. If this blood is not replaced, the patient can die.  Some diseases and treatments lower the number of red cells, so the patient does not have enough oxygen carrying cells. Some lower the number of platelets, which puts the patient at high risk of bleeding. Any of these complications can be life-threatening. A blood transfusion can be life-saving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Are there any substitutes for blood if I need a transfusion?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no substitutes for blood. This is why we are so grateful to the many family members and friends who donate blood for the benefit of our patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Is there anything to worry about after a transfusion?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allergic reactions can sometimes occur. Symptoms are listed below. They can occur up to 48 hours after the transfusion. Call your doctor immediately if you have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fever (100.4 F or 38 C or higher) or chills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flushing of the face.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hives, rash, or itching.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trouble breathing or shortness of breath.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low back pain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nausea or vomiting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weakness or fainting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blood in the urine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chest pain (If you have chest pain, call your local emergency number immediately.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Reference Section:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Facts About Blood&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blood is made up of plasma, which is 92 percent water, and three types of blood cells:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Red blood cells carry oxygen to the tissues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Platelets help form clots and stop bleeding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;White blood cells fight infection.
The number of each type of blood cell per volume of blood is calculated with a test called a complete blood count (CBC).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Red Blood Cells&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red blood cells carry oxygen to the tissues. We breathe in oxygen from the air and breathe out carbon dioxide. Hemoglobin in red blood cells carries oxygen from the lungs to the tissues in all parts of the body.  It then carries carbon dioxide from the tissues back to the lungs. A decrease in the number of red blood cells causes anemia. Anemia is diagnosed when the hemoglobin level is low. Signs and symptoms of anemia are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increased tiredness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generalized weakness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rapid heartbeat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shortness of breath&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Headache&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pale skin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you have anemia, your doctor may prescribe one or more of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A transfusion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adequate rest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A diet high in iron (e.g., green leafy vegetables, liver, chicken)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Iron supplements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Platelets&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Platelets help blood form clots and prevent bleeding. A low platelet count is called thrombocytopenia. The signs and symptoms are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nosebleeds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bleeding gums&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bruising&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small red spots on the skin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blood in the urine or stool&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bleeding that wont stop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you have thrombocytopenia, your doctor may suggest one or more of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brush your teeth with a soft toothbrush and floss your gums very gently or do not floss at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use an electric razor when shaving.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not play contact sports or engage in rough play.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not take aspirin, products containing aspirin, or other pain relievers such as ibuprofen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not use rectal suppositories, vaginal tampons, or take enemas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be very careful when using sharp instruments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wear gloves when gardening or cleaning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some thrombocytopenias are treated with a platelet transfusion; some require medication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;White Blood Cells&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White blood cells fight infection. A low white blood cell count is called leukopenia. If you have a low white blood cell count, you should take precautions to prevent infections from developing in your mouth, lungs, skin, or urinary tract. Your doctor or nurse will provide you with specific guidelines. Try also to avoid people with colds or other infections. The signs and symptoms of infection are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fever (100.4 F or 38 C or higher).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shaking or chills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sore throat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generalized achiness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burning sensation during urination.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you have leukopenia, your doctor may suggest one or more of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid crowds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid known sources of infection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monitor your temperature and report fever of 100? F (37.8 C) more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get adequate rest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use good hygiene.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions, please ask your doctor or nurse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doctor &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;___
Telephone &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nurse &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;____
Telephone &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 5 p.m. during the week and on weekends, or if you cannot reach your doctor, call the page operator at (212) 639-7900 and ask for the doctor covering your service.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
      <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://patiented.com/articles/when-your-doctor-recommends-a-transfusion"/>
      <id>http://patiented.com/articles/when-your-doctor-recommends-a-transfusion</id>
      <author>
        <name>MSKCC Patient Education</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>What You Need to Know About a Health Care Agent</title>
      <published>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</published>
      <updated>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;What is a health care agent?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A health care agent is someone you appoint to make health care decisions for you. Your health care agent can only
do this if you are unable to do it yourself. For example, if you are asleep during surgery, you could not make a health care decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Can I have more than one health care agent?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, medical decisions need to be made quickly. In that case, your doctor would want to speak with your health care agent as soon as possible. You may decide to appoint a second health care agent. Then, if your first choice was not available, your doctor could call the second choice. This person would assume the role only if the doctor could not reach your first choice. You can have only one person act for you at one time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What is a health care proxy form?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A health care proxy form lets you name your health care agent. You must sign and date the form. You must also have two witnesses sign it. You do not need a lawyer or a notary. You can write in what you would and would not want done if you could not make your own health care decisions. Give a copy of the form to your health care agent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What kinds of decisions can my health care agent make?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your health care agent can make most health care decisions for you if you cannot make them yourself. For example, your agent can decide if you should have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More treatment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Different treatment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No treatment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Are there things my health care agent cannot do?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your health care agent cannot make decisions for you if you are able to make them yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your health care agent cannot make financial decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your health care agent cannot decide about nutrition or fluids unless:
&lt;strong&gt; You have told your health care agent what you want or
&lt;/strong&gt; You have put your wishes about nutrition and fluids on your health care proxy form.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Who can I ask to be my health care agent?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can ask a family member, friend, or anyone you trust to be your health care agent. Your agent must be at least
18 years old. It cannot be your doctor or any other member of your health care team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How will my health care agent know what I want?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, you must ask the person you trust if he or she is willing to be your agent. Some people do not want that responsibility. Once you have chosen an agent, you must tell that person what you want. Some topics you should discuss with your agent are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would you want your health care team to try to restart your heart if it stops beating?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would you want to be on a respirator? (A respirator is a machine that helps your lungs to breathe.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would you want to have a feeding tube?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Your care goals may change over time. You may change your mind about what you do and do not want. Please keep your agent informed so he or she can follow your wishes. If your agent does not agree with the changes, you may appoint a new agent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What do I do with the health care proxy form?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important thing is to give it to your doctor. If you have more than one doctor, each one should have a copy. It will then be placed in your medical record so everyone who cares for you can see it. Give a copy of the proxy form to your agent(s). Your family members or friends should know who your agent is. Keep your own copy of the proxy form where your family can easily find it. Take a copy with you if you are admitted to a hospital or having surgery. Give it to the surgeon or nurse when you come for pre-surgical testing, or on the day of your surgery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What is the difference between a living will and a health care proxy form?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A living will gives specific instructions  to your health care team and to your agent. It tells them what you would and would not want if you could not make health care decisions yourself. A living will does not name someone to make health care decisions for you if you cannot make them yourself. This is what a health care proxy form does. You do not need a living will in New York.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get more information by calling a patient representative at (212) 639-7202.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can download healthcare proxy forms for New York State at: http://www.health.state.ny.us/professionals/
patients/health_care_proxy/intro.htm And at http://www.oag.state.ny.us/health/care_proxy.html
Caring Connections at www.caringinfo.org (800-658-8898) has forms for all states.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
      <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://patiented.com/articles/what-you-need-to-know-about-a-health-care-agent"/>
      <id>http://patiented.com/articles/what-you-need-to-know-about-a-health-care-agent</id>
      <author>
        <name>MSKCC Patient Education</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Using Electronic Mail with Your Nurse</title>
      <published>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</published>
      <updated>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Electronic mail (e-mail) is a good way to communicate with your nurse. You can use e-mail to ask your nurse about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Medicine and refills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nutrition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your treatment plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your test results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting more information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;However, you should be careful when sending e-mail. Use caution to ensure your safety and privacy.  This card has some basic information you should know about using e-mail. It also has guidelines you must follow to contact your nurse this way.  Please ask your nurse if you have any questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some situations when you should not use e-mail to communicate with your nurse. You should NOT send an e-mail:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To tell your nurse about symptoms or urgent matters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For matters that require a response the same day.  An example would be a prescription that needs a refill that day. It may take your nurse two business days to respond.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To tell your nurse about complicated issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To tell your nurse about highly private matters.
Instead, you should call your nurse or doctor to discuss any of these issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;General Concerns&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Privacy and security concerns about sending e-mail include:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The chance that an e-mail could be sent to a wrong address by mistake.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The chance that a third party could intercept a message between you and your nurse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The fact that your employer can legally access e-mails that you send from a work account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is always the chance that your e-mail will not be received because of a technical problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Guidelines For Sending An E-Mail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Type your full name, date of birth, and the purpose of your message in the subject box (field) of your e-mail.  For example: John Smith 4/27/76 lab results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When requesting a prescription refill, be sure to include:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The name and phone number of your pharmacy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The name of your medicine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The dosage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How often you take it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you need the refill.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your nurse will send you e-mail as a secure document.  This means that you will need to click on a link or copy the link and paste it on your internet browser to get the message.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you do not get a response within two business days, call your nurse or doctor on the phone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your nurse may share your e-mail with other staff in order to answer your questions. He or she may consult with:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A doctor.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another nurse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A dietitian.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A pharmacist.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Office staff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E-mails will become part of your medical record.  This means things that are communicated via e-mail are also noted in your files.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Using MyMSKCC&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of emailing your nurse, you can also use MyMSKCC.&lt;br/&gt;
MyMSKCC (https://my.mskcc.org) is a private, personalized online link to Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center. You can use it to get information about your care and communicate with your doctors office. To enroll in MyMSKCC, please contact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A session assistant in clinic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your physicians office.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The MyMSKCC Help Desk at mymskcc@mskcc.org or 646-227-2593.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goal is to respond to your questions or requests in a quick and helpful way.  Your nurses e-mail address is private. You should not share it with others unless your nurse approves. The above guidelines are to help ensure your safety and the correct response to your e-mail.  If the guidelines are not met, your nurse may ask that you communicate over the phone instead.  If you need to talk to your doctor or nurse about something important you should call rather than send an e-mail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NURSE _______________________________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E-MAIL ADDRESS _______________________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
      <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://patiented.com/articles/using-electronic-mail-with-your-nurse"/>
      <id>http://patiented.com/articles/using-electronic-mail-with-your-nurse</id>
      <author>
        <name>MSKCC Patient Education</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Transitioning Your Lymphoma Care from MSKCC to a Primary Care Doctor</title>
      <published>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</published>
      <updated>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At MSKCC we have a plan of care for our patients who have completed treatment for lymphoma. This plan is based on your individual needs. You have passed the time when most problems from lymphoma occur. As a result, you no longer need the care of lymphoma specialists. You are ready to transition your care to your local primary care doctor. As scary as this may seem, this is good news!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since you completed treatment for lymphoma, you have been receiving follow-up care from your lymphoma doctor. You may have had visits with more than one doctor depending on the treatments you received. Your lymphoma doctor focused on your long-term physical and emotional needs, such as taking care of any effects from your treatment.  After each of these visits, your lymphoma doctor sent information to your local primary care doctor. This was done to keep your local doctor informed so that at some time all your care could be transferred there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Frequently Asked Questions (Redundant)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How will my primary care doctor know about my lymphoma treatment?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your lymphoma doctor will send your local primary care doctor a detailed summary of your care at MSKCC. This report will include information about the treatment you received, your most recent test results, and recommendations for follow-up based your treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What other care will I need?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Treatment Related Screening&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes after treatment people develop other health problems, such as cardiovascular disease, thyroid disease, or cancer. Your lymphoma doctor will review specific recommendations for your follow up with you. We will also send this information to your local primary care physician. For information about cancer screening, refer to the booklet MSKCC Guidelines for Cancer Screening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;General Recommendations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the flu vaccine every year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the pneumonia vaccine every 5 years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have your cholesterol checked every year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continue to follow your doctors recommendations for diet and exercise and take medications as prescribed.
I see doctors at MSKCC for reasons not related to cancer. Can I continue?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you see physicians at MSKCC for diseases other than cancer, you may transfer that care to your primary care doctor or to a specialist in your community. You should talk to your MSKCC doctors and your primary care doctor about transferring your care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What if I have another lymphoma problem and need to come back?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any problems related to lymphoma or your lymphoma treatment, we want you to come to MSKCC. We will provide you and your primary care doctor with a phone number to call for an appointment.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
      <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://patiented.com/articles/transitioning-your-lymphoma-care-from-mskcc-to-a-primary-care-doctor"/>
      <id>http://patiented.com/articles/transitioning-your-lymphoma-care-from-mskcc-to-a-primary-care-doctor</id>
      <author>
        <name>MSKCC Patient Education</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Towards The End of Life - How You and Your Family Can Prepare</title>
      <published>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</published>
      <updated>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;By Susan Derby
With
S. Berenson, P. Brown, B. Cassileth, C. Finkel, R. Glassman, D. Glauner, C. Koehne,
M. Layman, T. Levin, M. Lofland, J. Mather, M. McDonough, F. Morrissey J. Pope,
P. Schaindlin, R. Schneider,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table of Contents
Introduction
Palliative Care
Hospice Care
Others Involved in Your End-of-Life Care&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Chaplains
Social Workers
Case Managers
Complementary Care
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychological Issues&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Coping Better: Talk Openly
Depression and Anxiety
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nutrition&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Hydration
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Help for Your Family
Common Symptoms at the End of Life
Confusion
Constipation
Death Rattle
Diarrhea
Difficulty Swallowing
Fatigue
Nausea and Vomiting
Pain
Shortness of Breath
Help for Children
Bereavement Services
If Death Occurs at Home
Conclusion
Introduction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  This booklet is for patients with advanced cancer who are moving towards the end of their lives. It is also for the people who care for and love them. You and your family may be wondering what lies ahead. We cannot tell you exactly, because patients have different symptoms and different needs at the end of life. This booklet will help you understand some of the symptoms you may experience towards the end of life and the options you have available to you.


  At Memorial Sloan-Kettering we want to make sure you understand your treatment options. By understanding your options you can make informed decisions about your care at the end of life. New York State has a new law that supports us in this effort. It is called the Palliative Care Information Act (2010). This law requires doctors and nurse practitioners to discuss the options with patients with a terminal illness. A terminal illness is one which is expected to result in death within six months. They must talk about the prognosis, treatment options, including the risks and benefits, and pain relief. Some patients are not able to make their own decisions about these things. The law requires us to give this information to a person with authority to make decisions for them. This is usually the person assigned by the patient on the Health Care Proxy Form. Your physician or nurse practitioner may not wish to talk with you about your care end of life options. In that case, he or she must arrange for anotherphysician or nurse practitioner to do so.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Palliative Care&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  Palliative care is an approach to caring for patients and their families.  Palliative care specialists are healthcare professionals who are expert in helping people optimize their quality of life when they are facing life-threatening or debilitating illnesses. Unlike hospice care, which is for people at the end of life, palliative care is provided as part of acute care, along with chemotherapy and other treatments.  

  Your primary cancer doctor can often provide palliative care during this time, but sometimes patients need more specialized palliative care. In this case, your primary doctor may call on the Memorial Sloan-Ketterings Pain and Palliative Care Service. The doctors, nurses and nurse practitioners from this service will work closely with your cancer doctors to make you comfortable. 

  At some point you and your doctor may decide that the goal of your care can longer be to cure your cancer. Instead the goal is to relieve your symptoms.  With the focus moved from cure to comfort, you and your family can concentrate on the quality of the time you have left. You might live for days, weeks, or many months. Palliative care aims to help you make the most of this time. 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hospice Care
Hospice care delivers palliative care to patients only at the end of life. The goals of hospice are:
* to help people live comfortably during the end stage of their life.
* to help them to have a peaceful death.&lt;br/&gt;
You might consider hospice care if your cancer no longer responds to treatment.  You might also consider it if the burden of treatment is greater than its benefit.  This is your decision. Your doctor may discuss hospice care with you and your family because it might be the care that best meets your needs at this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hospice care is delivered by a team of professionals.  A doctor is in charge of your care plan. Nurses are involved in your day-to-day care. You can receive help with physical needs, meals, and light housekeeping. A chaplain, social worker, and physical therapist can see you as needed. Hospice care may also include volunteers who can spend time with you. You can get this care:
* At home.
* In an assisted-living facility.
* In a nursing home.
* In a long-term care facility.
* In a hospital whose sole goal is to provide palliative care for cancer patients.
Hospice care includes ongoing symptom management.  All care is supervised by a hospice doctor and nurse. Hospice care may be paid for by Medicare, Medicaid, or private health insurance. Policies vary though; check with your insurer. Medicines for symptom control are covered as part of your care. If you are an inpatient, the care is 24 hours a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, hospice care in the home, does not provide 24-hour nursing care. A home health aide is usually provided for a certain number of hours several days per week. If you need additional help at home, you may have to pay for it. The hospice team helps your family to care for you.  A nurse is on call 24-hours a day to help with any problems and to advise you or your family over the phone.  If you go on hospice care, the hospice nurse will tell you what services will be provided. Ask your case manager about hospice care in your area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others Involved in Your End-of-Life Care
Many other specialists are important in making end-of-life care as peaceful and meaningful as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social Workers&lt;br/&gt;
Social workers provide emotional support and counseling. You and your family may need to make decisions on end-of life care. This can be difficult.  You can call on the social worker to assist you as you think about what you want.
Your social worker can also:
* assist with emotional support around issues such as change and loss.
* strengthen your and your familys coping skills.
* identify specific concerns that you or your family have.
* prepare and support you and your family for your death.
* help your family and members of the care team communicate.
* provide referrals to bereavement or support groups or community resources.
* counsel family members including children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Case Managers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Case managers are registered nurses. They assist you and your family with discharge planning. They can:
* arrange for services such as home care, home hospice, or placement in a care facility as needed.&lt;br/&gt;
* arrange for nursing visits, physical therapy, and social worker visits if these are needed.
* arrange for medical equipment if needed.
* help you find out what will and will not be covered by insurance.
They can work with you on the inpatient units and in the clinics.  When you are in the hospital, they work closely with your health care team. The case manager will help you find a home care agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chaplains
Spiritual and religious concerns may arise as death draws near. You may be religious.  You may be spiritual, but not religious. In either case, you may find it helpful if someone supports your beliefs. Spiritual needs at the end of life may include, but are not limited to:
* talking about the value and worth of your life in sacred terms.
* Taking part in prayer or ritual.
* hearing scripture or familiar sacred texts.
* finding comfort and grounding in sacred stories.
* seeking forgiveness, confessing grievances.
* connecting to faith communities.
Chaplains can offer prayer or a ritual or simply provide a comforting presence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our chaplains are able to assess your needs as you and your family face your death. They can walk the journey with you as a companion if you wish.  Clergy from the community are also available for many religious traditions.  We can arrange to have a clergy person from your faith visit at your request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our chapel is off the main lobby.  It is open day and night for prayer, meditation, or quiet contemplation.  All are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chaplains can be reached by calling (212) 639-5982.  The Chaplaincy Service Department is in room C-170.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complementary Care
Our Integrative Medicine Service offers complementary therapies. These comfort patients and families alike. They are non-invasive, reduce stress, and help control distress.
Pain, nausea, fatigue, anxiety, depression, and poor sleep are the most common complaints.  Many of our therapies can help control these and other symptoms. The Integrative Medicine Service will guide you and your family to the most appropriate and effective therapies. Among others, we offer massage, relaxation techniques, acupuncture, and hypnosis. In some cases, we teach family members to do light touch to sooth their loved one, or to learn guided imagery techniques. For a complete listing, please visit our web page at http://www.mskcc.org/mskcc/html/1979.cfm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treatments are free for MSKCC inpatients.  For MSKCC outpatients, or for family or friends, there is a charge.  Check with your insurance company to see if they reimburse for treatments. If you are an inpatient, call (212) 639-4947. Inpatient treatments are done at the bedside.  If you are an outpatient, call (212) 639-4700. Outpatient treatments are offered at 1429 1st Avenue at 74th St.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychological Issues
Many people want to remain in control no matter how sick they are. If you appoint a health care agent, you can make sure that your wishes are respected. If you have not appointed a health care agent, ask for the card What You Need to Know about a Health Care Agent and the booklet Health Care Decisions: Protect Yourself ?Plan Ahead.  It is possible that a time may come when you can no longer speak for yourself. In that case, you might want someone who knows your wishes to speak for you. That is what a health care agent can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coping Better: Talk Openly &lt;br/&gt;
Coping with worsening cancer is difficult.
As you become more dependent, your family and friends must work together to help you. If you and your family talk openly about death and dying, you are all likely to feel better. Not talking about what is happening simply avoids the subject. This is ultimately harmful. This sense of false hope  that everything will be all right  can seem hollow to the patient. The longer this goes on, the less time everyone has to say the things that matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking openly about death and dying also helps you and your family and friends to plan. If you can help loved ones to prepare for your death, this is of great benefit. Practical guidance may involve many areas. You can provide directions for burial and mourning. You can help with financial matters and delegate responsibilities. You can also give advice about how to move ahead with life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving ahead with life is an important task for your loved ones. Many patients think about it carefully. Family and friends may remember things that are said during this time forever.  Words that strengthen may guide family and friends on their journey through life. They will also lean on this strength when they themselves face the possibility of death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depression and Anxiety: They Are Treatable
Even though the time leading to death can be very difficult, most people cope well.   Feeling sad is normal, but depression is not. If you feel depressed for much of the day, let your doctor or nurse know. Depression can and should be treated. There are two main ways of treating depression and anxiety. One is talk therapy. The other is medication. Often these two approaches are used together. You must let your health care team know how you feel so they can help you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nutrition&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advanced cancer can cause many problems that can affect eating. In the final weeks of life, our goal is to keep you comfortable.  Symptoms you may have include:
* decreased desire for food.
* feeling full after only a few bites of food.
* taste changes.
* bloating or gas.
* dry mouth.
* difficulty swallowing.
* nausea or vomiting.
* constipation.
* fatigue and weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no rule on what foods you should be eating.  Eat the foods that appeal to you most.  If you were on a restricted diet before (e.g. diabetic diet), your doctor, nurse or dietitian may tell you to follow a less restrictive or regular diet.  That might give you more choices to enjoy your food and let you eat more. It is normal to eat and drink less and less as you get closer to death and your body slows down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Dry mouth may be a problem at this time. Some medicines you might be taking can make it worse.  You may find soft, moist foods and fluids most soothing.  Try:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;honeydew, cantaloupe, watermelon, or other fruits with high moisture content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;puddings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fruit yogurt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cottage cheese and fruit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ice cream, sherbet, popsicles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;soups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;macaroni and cheese.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;meat loaf with gravy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mashed potatoes with gravy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scrambled eggs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nutritional supplements or homemade milkshakes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Small, frequent meals are usually best. Large meals may be too filling or overwhelming.  Place reduced portions of food on salad plates or saucers.  That can make them more appealing.  Try small nibbles of food or sips of liquids throughout the day.  Keep your favorite foods on hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your family may encourage you to eat more. They may not have adjusted to the advanced stage of your cancer. At this point, food should be a source of enjoyment.  You are no longer eating for calories and protein.  Even if you eat well, you will not gain weight. That is the nature of cancer towards the end of life.  When you no longer enjoy food, meals may be stressful.
In the final days, the body may not use food or fluids as usual. If they are continued, you may feel uncomfortable.  It is normal to stop feeling thirsty and hungry.  Many patients refuse food towards the end of life. This is a normal process as death approaches. Forcing food and fluid at this time can cause harm. Death is the result of advanced disease, not of starvation. Your family and friends may find it helpful to speak to a dietitian, your doctor, nurse, or social worker to help them understand what is going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hydration&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you cannot eat or drink much, you can become dehydrated.  Symptoms of dehydration include dry mouth and skin, low urine output and dark, amber-colored urine.  Keeping the mouth clean and moist with wet swabs, crushed ice, or small sips of water can increase your comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You and your doctor will decide whether you should have intravenous fluids.  For some, hydration is a religious requirement.  In some instances, hydration may ease delirium. In other cases, dehydration has a soothing effect.  At the end of life intravenous fluid may make you feel worse, not better. It can increase secretions in your lungs. You may then cough more or have the sensation of choking. Large amounts of fluid can make your arms and legs swell.  This can make them feel heavy and make it hard for you to move. You and your doctor should talk about how you can get the right amount of fluid to keep you comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you and your doctor decide that intravenous hydration at home would be helpful to you, you will need the help of a nursing service and a home infusion company.  You will also need caregiver support.  Your case manager will arrange this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Help for Your Family
A physical or occupational therapist can work with your family members. The therapist can teach your family how to:
* position and turn you in bed and chairs.
* adjust your position to make you comfortable.
* help you transfer safely from bed to chair or from bed to commode.
* do passive exercises for your arms and legs. These can help you maintain some strength.
* use proper body mechanics so they do not harm themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common Symptoms at the End of Life
Let your doctor or nurse know if you are having any of the following symptoms. Early treatment makes them much easier to control.  It will also make you more comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confusion
As death approaches, some patients become confused and agitated. When people are confused, what they say may have no real meaning. They may see things that are not there. Your family should remember that this is not who you are. This is from the disease and what is happening to your body. Sometimes confusion leads to feeling threatened. A confused person may accuse family members of stealing or doing other bad things.  Again, this should not be taken on face value, as it is part of the illness. These symptoms should be treated aggressively. They can prevent a peaceful death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;   Treatment
Doctors treat confusion and agitation by addressing the underlying cause when possible. However, there may be many causes for these symptoms at the end of life.  Whatever the cause, the symptoms must be treated. Usually this involves medicines that help to calm the person.  The medicines may also help you think more clearly.
   Things Your Family Can Do
* Keep the room well lit during the day.
* Place a clock close by so you can be aware of the time.
* Place a calendar or clearly visible note that identifies the date - Today is Thursday, January 1, 2011.
* Minimize noise levels in the room.
* Continue to help you wear your hearing aids or glasses when possible.
* Administer pain medicine.
* Communicate clearly.
* Explain all actions before they are done  I am going to turn you now.
* Make sure familiar objects are in the room.
* Manage constipation by following the doctors directions.
* Promote relaxation and sleep.
* Administer oxygen if ordered.
* Administer medication to treat confusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constipation
Constipation is not having your usual number of bowel movements. You may not empty your bowel completely. You may have trouble passing hard stool. It can be an uncomfortable side effect of many medicines. The most common are those to treat pain, nausea, and depression, but other medicines can also cause it. It can also be caused by the disease itself as the tumor grows and affects different organs. Diet and decreased activity can make it worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;   Treatment
Take over-the-counter medicines such as stool softeners and laxatives. You do not need a prescription. Docusate sodium (Colace) is a stool softener and senna (Senekot) is a laxative.  Ask your doctor what to take and how much. If these do not work, tell your doctor or nurse. You may need a prescription for something stronger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;   Things you can do
Try to drink fluids if you can.  Include water, juices, soups, and ice cream. Eat foods with fiber. Examples are fruits, vegetables, whole grains, and cereals containing fiber. As you get closer to the end of your life, changes in your diet will not be possible because you will be eating less. Dont force yourself to try to do what you cannot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diarrhea
Diarrhea is watery bowel movements. At the end of life, both the disease and its treatment can cause diarrhea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;   Treatment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask your doctor if you can take over-the-counter medicine. Examples are:
* Loperamide (Imodium)
* Bismuth subsalicylate (Pepto Bismol or Kaopectate)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;   Things You Can Do&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increase the amount of fluid you drink if your doctor wants you to prevent dehydration from loss of water. Drink clear liquids such as apple juice, water, broth, and ices. Try sucking on ice pops. Keep your mouth moist with a small amount of ice chips if you cannot swallow. Keep your lips moistened with lip balm if you cannot drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoid milk and other dairy products. Do not eat foods that are irritating, such as spicy foods. Eat frequent, small meals whenever possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Products are available for adults who are active despite diarrhea. Adult incontinent pads can be used when you are in bed. You can find these products in your pharmacy and some grocery stores. They include:
? Depends
? Teva (Serenity)
It is important to change pads frequently to prevent skin breakdown. It is also important to keep the rectal area clean. Wash with gentle soap and water. Apply ointment after each diarrheal movement.  Ointments you can use include:
? A&amp;amp;D
? Balmex
? Desitin ointment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficulty Swallowing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have a feeling that your food is stuck in your throat. You may cough after swallowing. This can mean the food is getting into your lungs. This is called aspiration. It can cause pneumonia.  These symptoms are more common in patients whose cancer is in the chest or neck. Tell your doctor or nurse if you have these symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Treatment
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your doctor may tell you it is not safe to eat or drink at all.  In that case, intravenous hydration by vein may be considered. (See Hydration, page XX.)
   Things You Can do
You may need only a change of diet. It includes chopping your food or pureeing it to make it easier to swallow. You might also use a thickening agent such as Thicken-Up to make it safe for you to swallow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fatigue&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fatigue is a persistent sensation of tiredness or lack of energy.  It is the most common symptom at the end of life.  It can range from mild to severe. Patients often tell us they cannot walk even short distances.  It is important to try to minimize fatigue because this symptom can worsen others such as depression, sadness, and feelings of loss. All of these are common at the end of life.
Pain often makes fatigue worse. Ignoring or trying to endure pain may cause stress and intensify fatigue.  Do not wait until your pain level is high to take pain medicine.  It is better to take it when pain is at a 3 or 4 level on a 0 to 10 scale. When you have less pain, you are likely to be more at peace.  You may even be interested in other activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Treatment 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Medicines may help with fatigue. You can take these when you need them. You do not have to take them every day. Your doctor or nurse practitioner can prescribe them for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anti-anxiety medicines or antidepressants may help you feel better overall. Ask your doctor if you should try them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sadness is the emotion that expresses loss. This emotion can affect fatigue.  Discuss it with your family members and friends.  Tell your doctor, nurse, social worker, or chaplain.  If they understand how you are feeling, they can be of help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;  Things You Can Do&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sitting up or getting out of bed may help to lessen fatigue if you have a hard time walking. However, try to walk short distances every day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading, writing, or doing another activity may keep you involved.  This can lessen your fatigue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fatigue is likely to affect your quality of sleep.  It might help to take 20 or 30 minute naps during the day. Take them before 3 p.m. That will lower the chance of your not sleeping at night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conserve your energy. Dont be afraid to ask for help with simple things such as bathing or even eating.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nausea and Vomiting
Nausea and vomiting are symptoms that may occur at the end of life. Nausea may begin as an unpleasant wave-like feeling. It may or may not result in vomiting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Treatment
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can usually give you something to control nausea and vomiting. Medicines can be pills or rectal suppositories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Things You Can Do
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do not attempt to eat until the symptom subsides. It may be helpful to drink fluids such as warm tea, which you may be able to tolerate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Constipation can cause nausea and vomiting; try to prevent it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;? Try to drink fluids, if you can. . Ask your doctor how much fluid you should be drinking.
? Walk if possible.
? Take over-the-counter medicines to soften your stools if your doctor or nurse says it is okay.
* If you feel that your pain medicine is causing your nausea and vomiting, let your doctor or nurse know. They may be able to change the medicine.
* Eat small meals and avoid highly spicy foods. These may trigger nausea due to their smell.
* Try room temperature or cold foods that are bland.
* Consider trying other techniques such as acupuncture, relaxation, distraction, and hypnosis.  You can do relaxation, distraction, and hypnosis in your home once you become familiar with them. Our Integrative Medicine Service can teach you some of these techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effective pain management is a big part of end of life care. Tell your doctor or nurse if you are having any new pain or if your pain gets worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Treatment
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take your pain medicine by mouth as long as you can. If you have difficulty swallowing your pills, the medicine can be given in other ways.  Even at the end of life some patients can receive radiation therapy to relieve bone pain. It can also be used to shrink a tumor that causes pain by pressing on nerves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Things You Can Do
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk to your doctor and nurse.  Some people worry that taking a lot of pain medicine may cause addiction or hasten death. Let your doctor or nurse know if you have these concerns.   Your doctors and nurses want to make you as comfortable as possible when you are dying. This includes aggressively controlling your pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Restlessness or Agitation
At the end of life some patients may be restless and agitated. This may be associated with pain or confusion. It may occur on its own. These symptoms can vary in intensity. Your doctor or nurse should always be notified. There may be many causes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  Treatment
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main treatment is medicine. . It can be given by mouth or under the tongue. It should be given around the clock. The goal is to keep you safe and calm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Things Your Family Can Do
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place familiar objects around you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep the room well lit and place a clock where you can see it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talk calmly and softly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimize doing anything that makes you uncomfortable or fearful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduce external stimulation such as loud television or radio if they interfere with your sleep.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Shortness of Breath (Dyspnea)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortness of breath is common at the end of life. It feels as if you cannot get enough air.  It is most common in patients with lung cancer, but can occur in other cancers. There may be more than one cause of your shortness of breath.
Shortness of breath can vary in its severity.  You may only become short of breath when climbing stairs or you may feel that way when at rest.  Report this symptom to your doctor or nurse.  It can be treated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Treatment 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treatment of shortness of breath depends on the underlying problem. Your doctor may remove fluid that is pressing on your lungs. You might need a blood transfusion. You may get medicine to relax the muscles in your airways. Oxygen will help some people.  Your doctor or nurse will have many ways to improve this symptom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Things You Can Do
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of steps you can take to relieve your discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan for periods of rest between activities to help you catch your breath.  If talking makes your breathing worse, shorten your time with visitors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find a comfortable position.  Sitting up makes breathing easier.  Try using a foam wedge or backrest when lying in bed.  Sleeping or napping in a recliner may also make you feel more comfortable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open a window or use a fan to keep air moving in the room.  This often makes people feel like they are getting more air.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the winter, use a humidifier.  People often breathe through their mouths when they feel short of breath.  This causes dryness of the mouth.  Humidifying the air may make you more comfortable.  You may also benefit from drinking warm beverages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do any activity that helps you to calm down and relax. Try prayer, meditation, music, or relaxation exercises. These have all helped others. You can also combine them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is important to tell your doctor and nurse how effective the treatment is.  If you are still feeling short of breath after one kind of treatment, there may be other steps they can take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Death Is Near
At the end of life you will become more fatigued. You:
* may remain in bed for longer periods during the day.
*  are likely to talk less and when you do it will be in a whisper.
* may have little desire to eat or drink.
Your body temperature will become cooler. Breathing may become shallow. A sigh may be followed by a period of no breathing. This pattern may continue for some time, often hours. Your skin color may change and become paler or grayish. The circulation in your hands and feet will decrease and they may become cool to touch. During the last hours of life, you may not speak and may seem to be in a coma or sleeping. Nevertheless,   you may still be able to hear voices.
Death Rattle
In the last hours of life, you may develop a rattle in your breathing.  This happens because saliva or fluids collect in the throat or upper airways. It may not make you uncomfortable, but it may worry family members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;   Treatment
Your doctor or nurse can order medicine to decrease the secretions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;   Things Your Family Can Do
They can change your position to see if that stops it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Help for Children
A serious illness in the family will affect the children.  It does not matter how young or old they are. Your instinct may be to protect your child from the sadness and confusion that you are feeling. However, it is better to be honest about what is happening. Let your children know that this important person in their life is very sick and may die soon. What they understand will vary. Much depends on their age and maturity. All children will feel the pain in their own way.It might be helpful to let children take part in the end-of-life process.Telling your children the truth right now will help them know they can trust you. Spend some time answering their questions. Try to make it clear that if they have more questions later, you will answer them.  If you are having trouble talking to your children, ask a family member or friend to help you. There are also counselors who can help you with this. Please call the MSKCC Department of Social Work at (212) 639-7020 and ask for a referral. You can also call the MSKCC Counseling Center at (646) 888-0100.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MSKCCs Kids Express Program publishes a brochure that will give you some tips on how to talk to your children about your cancer. Ask your nurse or social worker for a copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bereavement Services
After a patient dies, the social worker can:
* help your family with sad feelings.
* meet with your family to help them with any plans that are needed.
* tell your family about bereavement services offered at MSKCC.
* tell your family about other services in the community that can help during this difficult time.
You can learn more about the MSKCC Bereavement Program by calling (646) 888-4889.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Death Occurs at Home
The team that has been involved with your care will guide your family. This may be the home hospice nurse, or it may be the MSKCC staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conclusion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to think about dying.  But many people believe it can be a time of growth and closeness with family and loved ones. Death is different for everyone. We can assist in controlling symptoms as well as helping with the emotional and spiritual distress. Our goal is to help you and your loved ones through this time with comfort, peace, and dignity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resources that may be useful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;American Cancer Society, Inc. Caring for the Patient with Cancer at Home  A Guide for Patients and Families. Atlanta: American Cancer Society, Inc., 2000.
http://www.cancer.org/docroot/MBC/MBC_2x_OtherEffects.asp
Call 800-ACS-2345 for a free copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coping with Advanced Cancer (National Cancer Institute)
http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/advancedcancer
Call 800-4-CANCER for a free copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End-of-Life Care: Questions and Answers (National Cancer Institute)
http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/factsheet/Support/end-of-life-care
Call 800-4-CANCER for a free copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;End of Life Issues (U.S. National Library of Medicine)
http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/endoflifeissues.html
Resources are available in Spanish and Chinese languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Days of Life (PDQ) (National Cancer Institute)
http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/pdq/supportivecare/lasthours/patient/allpages
Call 800-4-CANCER for a free copy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transitional Care Planning (PDQ) (National Cancer Institute)
http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/pdq/supportivecare/transitionalcare/patient/allpages
Call 800-4-CANCER for a free copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Someone You Love Has Advanced Cancer: Support for Caregivers (National Cancer Institute)
http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/when-someone-you-love-has-advanced-cancer
Call 800-4-CANCER for a free copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2011 Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center
1275 York Avenue, New York, NY 10065&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
      <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://patiented.com/articles/towards-the-end-of-life-final"/>
      <id>http://patiented.com/articles/towards-the-end-of-life-final</id>
      <author>
        <name>MSKCC Patient Education</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Total Body Irradiation</title>
      <published>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</published>
      <updated>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You will have radiation therapy before your bone marrow or stem cell transplant. This booklet tells you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why you will have it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How it is planned and given.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The possible side effects you may have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Purpose Of Radiation Therapy Before Transplant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many patients have total body irradiation (TBI) before transplant. It is delivered to the entire body. It is given for any or all of the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To destroy cancer cells in areas not easily reached by chemotherapy. These are the nervous system, bones, skin, and testes in men.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To decrease the response of your immune system. If you are getting bone marrow or stem cells from a donor, your body may see these as foreign. The immune system tries to destroy cells that are foreign to your body. TBI is done so that the immune system wont destroy these cells.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To create space for the new marrow to grow (engraft).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Simulation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will first meet with the radiation oncologist and nurse. They will discuss your treatment and answer any questions you have. You will then begin the planning session for your treatment. It is called simulation. This generally takes two to four hours. You do not have to do anything to prepare for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Simulation Day&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wear comfortable clothes and make sure not to wear earrings or necklaces. The radiation therapist will greet you. He or she will take a photograph of your face. This is placed in your folder and used to identify you throughout your treatment. The procedure will be explained to you and you can ask any questions. You will need to sign a consent form if you have not done it already. Your doctor will review this part of your treatment with you before you sign the consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will need to undress from the waist up and change into a gown. Keep your shoes on. The therapist(s) will help you lie on a table. Although it will have a sheet on it, the table is hard and has no cushion. The temperature in the room is usually cool. Let the therapists know if it is too cool and you are uncomfortable. Throughout simulation, you will feel the table move to different positions. The lights in the room will be turned on and off and you will see red laser lights on each wall. The therapist(s) use these laser lights as a guide when they position you on the table. Do not look directly into the red beam as this may hurt your eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The therapists will walk in and out of the room during the simulation. You will hear the therapists speaking to each other as they work. They will tell you what they are doing. Please do not speak once they begin, unless you are uncomfortable or need help. Speaking may alter your position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music can be played throughout the simulation. If you would like, ask a radiation therapist to play a CD for you. You may bring a CD from home if you prefer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;X-ray Images&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;X-ray images will be taken of your chest. They are done with an x-ray machine called a simulator. You will be standing up for these x-rays. It takes about 20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Skin Markings (Tattoos)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The therapists will draw on your skin with a felt marker that can be washed off after simulation. These marks will be used to make the permanent skin markings called tattoos. To make the tattoos, the therapists will use a sterile needle and a drop of ink. The tattoo marks are no bigger than the head of a pin. The sensation of getting one feels like a pinprick. You will receive two tattoos, one on your upper back and one on your upper chest. They are permanent so you will not need to worry that they will wash off in the shower. Some photographs will be taken of you after you get the tattoos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;CT Scan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will then be brought to another room for a CT scan. The CT scan is used to map your treatment plan. You will hear the machine as it is turned on and off. Even if the noise seems loud, the therapists will be able to hear you if you need to speak with them. The CT scan takes about 10 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Treatment Planning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After your simulation, a team will plan your treatment using your x-ray and CT scan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lungs are very sensitive to radiation. They cannot get the same dose that the rest of your body will receive. To protect them, lung blocks will be made. They will decrease the dose of radiation that your lungs receive. The chest x-rays you had are used to make the blocks. These blocks will be placed on a screen in front of your body during each treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bones in the portion of the chest wall located behind these blocks contain a great deal of bone marrow. These areas must receive a full dose of radiation. You will receive radiation to the chest wall, front and back, without the blocks, once a day for two days of your treatment. The images taken of your chest will be used to plan the treatment to your chest wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The details from simulation are planned and checked. This takes between five days and two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;TBI TREATMENT&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be admitted to the hospital. Your TBI will be given in divided treatments. The treatment schedule depends on the type of TBI you will have. Treatment will be given:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Monday through Friday twice a day (at about 8 a.m. and 4 p.m.) or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tuesday through Friday three times a day (at about 8 a.m., 1 p.m., and 6 p.m.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Wear lightweight, loose-fitting clothes when you go to treatment. Clothes should not have any metal. You can keep your socks on if you wish, but you must take off your shoes or slippers. Do not wear any jewelry or metal objects (rings, hairpins). These may increase the radiation dose to that area. CD players are in the room. You may bring a CD to play during your treatment if you would like. A VCR is also available. If you would prefer to watch a videotape, you may bring one. You can also chose from the ones we have in our department. An escort will bring you to your treatments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your treatment is given by radiation therapists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Positioning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must be in the correct position during treatment. Infants and very small children will be wrapped in a papoose board on a table. Older children and adults are positioned standing on a platform. You will stand over a bicycle-like seat with your hands placed on bars on either side of your hips. (Figure1) The radiation therapists will help you. You will face the machine for the first half of your treatment and will be turned away from it for the second half. The lung blocks are placed on a board that hangs in front of your chest. They do not touch your body. The tattoos you got during simulation will be used to place the blocks. A large Plexiglass screen is placed in the front of your body before the treatment begins. It assures that the treatment is evenly distributed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Description of Treatment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The radiation therapists will leave the room when you are in position. Breathe normally, but do not to move during the treatment. If you move, the treatment will not be evenly distributed. You may hear the machine click as it turns on and off, but you will not feel anything. Having a radiation treatment feels like having an x-ray. It is painless. The treatments take about 15 to 20 minutes. Some patients find it helpful to listen to music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although you are alone during your treatment, the radiation therapist will watch you on a TV screen. They can talk to you over an intercom system (Figure 2). They can hear you if you have any questions or problems during the treatment. If at any point you are not feeling well, tell them. The treatment can be stopped. The therapist will come into the room to help you. Your treatment will be restarted once you are feeling better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You and your clothes do not become radioactive during or after treatment. It is safe for you to be around other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Additional Treatments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extra doses of radiation may be given to specific areas of the body. This is called a boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some boosts may be given before you are hospitalized for TBI and transplant. These may be to the:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spleen in patients with chronic leukemia who have an enlarged spleen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fluids that bathe the brain and spinal cord if your doctor thinks cancer cells may be in these areas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some boosts are given while you are getting TBI. These are to the:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chest wall, front and back, without the blocks, once a day for two days of your treatment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Testes in male patients who have acute leukemia or myelodysplastic syndrome. This is often on the last day. You will be lying down for the treatment with your penis and scrotum exposed. The treatment does not cause any pain or discomfort.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Side Effects Of Treatment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will not feel any pain during the treatment, but TBI has side effects. Some occur right away or during the four days of treatment. Some occur days or weeks after your treatment. And some occur months after TBI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the treatment, the most common side effects include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Headache&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nausea and vomiting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diarrhea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fatigue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A skin reaction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Less common is swelling of the salivary glands. This causes pain in front of the ear and in the jaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medicines can decrease nausea and vomiting. These side effects are most severe during the first day of radiation. They usually begin one to two hours after the first treatment. If you vomit, it usually becomes less frequent as the treatment proceeds. It often stops by the third day. You may also have diarrhea during the first few treatment days. Tell your nurse if you have any symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the days of your treatment, you may not use any:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lotions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ointment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deodorants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Before you come to the hospital buy Aquaphor. Apply this to your entire body each night after your last treatment. Some patients develop a mild reddening of the skin during the first few days of treatment. After radiation is completed, your skin may feel dry and itchy. If you received a boost to the testes, the reaction may be more severe in the scrotal area. Continue to use the Aquaphor after your TBI treatments are over until your skin returns to normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of side effects you may get during the days and weeks after your TBI. These also may be from the chemotherapy you have received. They include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hair loss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discomfort in the throat and mouth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change in taste.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mouth sores.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nausea and vomiting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diarrhea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bone marrow suppression (low blood counts).
These will go away over time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;TBI can cause long-term side effects. They can occur months or years after your transplant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sterility is an expected side effect. Sexual function and pleasure will not be affected. Please talk to your doctor or nurse about any concerns you have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;About half of the patients will need thyroid supplements.
Other long-term side effects are rare, but can occur. They include:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inflammation of the sac that surrounds the heart.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inflammation of the lungs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cataracts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second malignancies or new cancers.
Please discuss these side effects with your doctor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Emotional Concerns&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having cancer is likely to cause you and the people who care about you to react in many ways. You may feel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anxious&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Afraid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nervous&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Down&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Depressed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worried&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Numb&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ambivalent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Angry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;All these feelings are expected if you or someone you love has a serious illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may also worry about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Telling your employer that you have cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paying your medical bills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How your family relationships may change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The effect of cancer or treatment on your body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whether you will continue to be sexually attractive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The cancer coming back.
When people try to protect each other by hiding their feelings, they can feel very alone. It might help to talk about your feelings. Talking can help the people around you know what you are thinking. It can bring you closer at a time when support is so needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Each of us has our own way of responding to difficult situations. Generally we use whatever has worked for us in the past. However, sometimes this is not enough. We encourage you to speak with your doctor, nurse, and social worker about your concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;After You Complete Your Treatment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you leave the hospital, you will be closely followed. You will have regular appointments with your doctors. These visits let us see how you responded to treatment. Blood tests, x-rays, and scans may also be ordered during these visits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bring a list of any questions and concerns you have. Also bring a list of all your medicines. If you are running low on any medicine, let your doctor know before you run out. Call your doctor or nurse any time if you have any questions or problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope this booklet has been helpful in preparing you for TBI. If you have any questions, please speak with your radiation oncologist or nurse. Below are important telephone numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monday to Friday 9AM to 5PM&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radiation Oncologist  &lt;br/&gt;
Telephone &lt;br/&gt;
Radiation Nurse
Telephone&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any problems that must be addressed in the evenings or over the weekend, please call ____________________ and ask for the radiation oncologist on call.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
      <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://patiented.com/articles/total-body-irradiation"/>
      <id>http://patiented.com/articles/total-body-irradiation</id>
      <author>
        <name>MSKCC Patient Education</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Sperm Collection by Testicular Sperm Extraction (TESE)</title>
      <published>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</published>
      <updated>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;TESE is a procedure to collect sperm directly from the testes if no sperm are found in the semen. This may be needed because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The testes are not able to make enough sperm to find in the semen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a blockage that prevents sperm from passing out of the penis during ejaculation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Men may have this procedure done before cancer treatment, to preserve their fertility potential, or after cancer treatment, to attempt fathering a child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Before the Procedure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TESE is performed in the Surgical Day Hospital. Please speak with your doctor or nurse about how you should prepare for surgery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Description of the Procedure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be given general anesthesia so you will be asleep during the procedure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The doctor makes a very small incision in your scrotum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The testes are examined using a tiny surgical microscope to locate areas where sperm may be found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small pieces of tissue are removed from the testes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The incision is closed with sutures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A compression dressing will be placed around your scrotum. A scrotal support will be put on to hold this in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will recover in the Post Anesthesia Care Unit until you wake up. Then you will be discharged home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pieces of tissue that were removed are broken into pieces and placed into vials. These will be delivered
to The Sperm Bank of New York where they will analyze the sample. If sperm are found, the tissue will be transferred to their affiliated New Jersey sperm bank for freezing and storage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The address of the sperm bank is:
The Sperm and Embryo Bank of New Jersey 187 Mill Lane
Mountainside, NJ 07092
908-654-8836&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;After the Procedure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What to expect&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mild pain and tenderness in your scrotum for a few days. You will be given a prescription for pain medicine. Take this as directed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mild bruising (black and blue appearance) on your scrotum and penis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;How to care for your scrotum&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first 2 days after surgery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep the compression dressing in place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep the scrotal support in place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply cold packs against the dressing (outside of the dressing but inside the scrotal support). Keep these on continuously for 48 hours except for when you sleep.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On the third day after surgery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove the scrotal support and dressing. Take a shower.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reapply the scrotal support and keep it on continuously for 1 week. You can remove it when you shower.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Activity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first 2 days after surgery, stay off your feet as much as you can. You can walk short distances within your home. You can climb stairs as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When sitting, elevate your legs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not drive while you are taking pain medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not lift any heavy objects (10 pounds or greater) for at least 2 weeks after surgery.
Call your doctor if you have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A fever over 101F (38.3C).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pain not relived by your pain medicine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
      <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://patiented.com/articles/tese"/>
      <id>http://patiented.com/articles/tese</id>
      <author>
        <name>MSKCC Patient Education</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Steroid Injections</title>
      <published>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</published>
      <updated>2012-10-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This information will help prepare you for your steroid injection (shot).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A steroid injection is given to relieve pain and reduce inflammation and swelling. The injection can be given into your joint or into the area around your joint. It may take 3 to 4 days for you to feel the effects of the steroid. These effects usually last 3 to 4 weeks or longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common sites for steroid injections are the:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shoulder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hip&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wrist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Steroid injections are most commonly given for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arthritis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Injury&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tendonitis (inflammation in a tendon)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bursitis (inflammation in the area around a joint)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Before Your Procedure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tell your doctor the following information before your procedure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are taking any:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prescribed or over-the-counter medications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Herbal medications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vitamins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dietary supplements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDS), such as aspirin, ibuprophen (Advil), and naproxen (Aleve)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Medicines that prevent blood clotting such as:
&lt;strong&gt; Warfarin (Coumadin)
&lt;/strong&gt; Clopidogrel bisulfate (Plavix)
&lt;strong&gt; Tinzaparin sodium (Innohep)
&lt;/strong&gt; Dalteparin sodium (Fragmin)  Heparin
** Chemotherapy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you are allergic to:
* Any medications
* Latex
* Adhesive tape
* Lidocaine
* Antiseptic solution&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have an infection anywhere in your body&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have to stop taking some medications before your procedure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day before your procedure, someone will call you and tell you the time and location of your procedure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Day of Your Procedure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your doctor will go over the risks and benefits of having the steroid injection and ask you to sign a consent form.
You will be given a gown and asked to remove any clothing that covers the affected joint. You will be put in
a position that allows your doctor to give you your injection. He or she may use an ultrasound to help find the best place for your injection. Your doctor will then clean the area and inject a mixture of the steroid and a numbing medication.
Most patients say that the injection is not painful. Any discomfort should go away in a few minutes as the numbing medication starts working. The numbing medication usually wears off in 6 to 8 hours. At this time, you may feel some soreness in your joint. It may last for up to 48 hours until the steroid medication starts to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use cold packs to help reduce any discomfort. You can use them several times a day as needed on a schedule of no more than 10 minutes on and 10 minutes off. Do not use them if you have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Problems with blood supply such as Raynauds Disease  Problems related to poor circulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nerve problems with poor sensation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;After Your Procedure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep a dry and clean bandage/Band-Aid over the injection site for 24 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site may be sore for a few days. Ask your doctor about taking pain medication.  Ask your doctor if there are any activities or movements that you should avoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not use hot/warm packs on the site for 24 hours after your injection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Call Your Doctor or Nurse If You:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a temperature of 100.1 F (38.3 C) or higher&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have pain or swelling at the injection site that does not start to feel better after 48 hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Call Your Doctor or Nurse If You Develop:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skin irritation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increased redness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Warmth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Itching around the injection site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have any new or unexplained symptoms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have any questions or concerns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The information on this card does not cover all possible side effects; others may occur. Please report any problems to your doctor.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
      <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://patiented.com/articles/steroid-injections"/>
      <id>http://patiented.com/articles/steroid-injections</id>
      <author>
        <name>MSKCC Patient Education</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
</feed>